Welcome back. In
an earlier video,
we learned about how to
identify risks when
planning projects.
In this module, we'll learn
why risks and changes might
occur during a project and how
that can impact your
project's scope.
You may remember that a risk is
a potential event that might
occur and could
impact your project.
When you think about risks in
the context of
project management,
you'll think about
them as hypothetical.
In other words, these might not
be events that will
definitely happen,
but because there's a possibility
that they could happen,
it's your responsibility
as a project manager
to identify and plan
for those risks.
Let's revisit some
examples of risks.
A project risk might be
a contractor missing a deadline,
or introducing a tool that may
lead to communication
breakdown within your team,
or unexpected,
additional work because
of an unforeseen policy
being put in place.
When any risk occurs,
the consequence is a change
to the project plan.
A change is anything that
alters or impacts the tasks,
structures, or processes
within a project.
Changes are typically unexpected.
More often than not,
they have a negative
impact on the project,
and you'll have to
learn to navigate that.
But sometimes, and I'm placing
a heavy emphasis on sometimes,
changes can have a
positive impact.
Changes can encompass
any variance from
the original project plan in
regards to the triple constraint.
This may entail changing
priorities and scope,
budget and resources, or changes
to the project timeline.
We'll discuss how the internal
and external dependencies
of a project impact each
other and bring about change.
Let's go through a few types of
changes that can
affect your project.
Some examples of changes may
include new or
changing dependencies.
Dependencies are
tasks, activities,
or milestones that are
reliant on one another.
So if one task isn't
completed on time,
it may put your
other tasks behind.
You might be in
charge of renovations
on a home where there
are dependencies.
In a bathroom remodel,
for instance,
a new sink cannot be installed
until the vanity and
plumbing are in place.
Next, is changing priorities.
The scope of the
remodel changes if
your client's in-laws
suddenly have to move in,
and you have to move
up planned work on
the spare bedroom before
completing the bathroom remodel.
Next up, the capacity and
people available could change.
Maybe you have to
replace the plumber
because you had issues
on the job site.
Another type of
change could include
a new limitation on your
budget or resources.
For example, you need to
reduce design costs
in the new bathroom
by 10 percent because
your quotes for
electrical work come in
higher than expected.
Another change could
be scope creep.
Scope creep is when changes,
growth, and other factors
affect the project scope.
For instance, your clients
are so happy with the tile in
the new bathroom
that they'd like to
replace the tile in all
of their bathrooms.
Finally, force majeure.
This is another change
that could occur due
to a national or
international crisis.
If you aren't familiar
with this term,
it means an unforeseen
circumstance that prevents
someone from fulfilling
the contract
due to a major crisis.
Force majeure is pretty uncommon.
But for instance, if a
union goes on strike,
certain vendors won't be able
to fulfill their contracts.
If there's a pandemic,
all production on your new
product might be halted.
Changes should be
measured against
the baseline estimates of scope,
budget, and time allotted for
your project, given the
original requirements.
Be mindful that when you change
any one of those things,
there may be knock-on
effects which
could be positive or negative.
For instance, your
clients may believe they
have beautiful hardwood
floors hiding underneath
old living room carpet
and want to pull up
the old carpet and use
the original hardwood
floors underneath.
You, the project manager
on this particular
construction job—you've
budgeted to have
the carpet removed and
the old floors sanded
and stained. Bad news.
You pull up the carpet and find
the floors are in bad
shape and rotting.
They'll need to be
replaced or repaired,
which could be costly,
so your timeline and budget
are likely to take a hit.
When it comes to who takes on
the responsibility of
managing the changing scope,
it'll be you—the
project manager.
But depending on the project,
you probably won't do it alone.
In order to properly
manage changes,
you'll want to refer
to documents like
your Statement of Work
and the RACI chart.
But you might also have to
create some new documentation.
You'll want to create or
familiarize yourself with
the processes for requesting
changes for your team
or organization.
These processes might include
a change request form.
Let's discuss change
request forms.
You and your stakeholders will
use these forms in order to stay
on top of, and adequately
manage, any changes.
Since a lot of people
with different roles
on the project can
fill out these forms,
it's important for
the forms to be
self-explanatory
and very thorough.
In the provided template,
which uses a 2-by-10 table,
you'll need to include
information in the cells,
such as: the project name,
the discussion owner, who's
taking the lead on this
discussion from the team,
discussion type.
You'll want to let
your audience know if you'll
be discussing a risk,
opportunity, or anything else.
You'll want to identify the teams
involved and the expected
outcome of the discussion,
which might be a change in
priorities, schedule change,
or an official call
on how to proceed
with an issue. Add
the target date for
discussion, and identify
which milestones
or goals might be impacted.
Provide a short description of
the current situation,
the change,
and any difference you
expect to make to
the plan of record,
like a snapshot of
the before and after.
Then go into in-depth
proposal for
the necessary changes and
address any trade-offs.
Finally, provide any
background information
so that everyone shares
the same context.
You can also refer to your
statement of work, or SOW,
for more information about who
needs to be involved
in that conversation.
If you find that one or more of
your milestones are at risk
of not being completed,
then you'll need
to get a customer
sign-off before the scope,
deadline, or budget are changed,
and all parties involved
need to be informed.
Great work. We've reviewed how
to define risk and
know more about how
to identify the reasons why risks
and changes might occur
during a project.
And now we can explain the impact
of increasing a project scope.
In the next video, we're going
to discuss the role dependencies
play and how to properly
manage them. We'll
meet you there.